Abraham: So, what exactly are
networks and what do they do?
Let’s look at these in more detail.
Nicole: A LAN or Local Area Network
connects devices such as personal
computers and workstations that
share tools, data and programmes.
These may be in homes, schools, hospitals
and small businesses and may use an
ethernet protocol to define how the
information moves around the network.
They are connected using a
private addressing scheme as
defined by the TCP/IP protocol.
For increased speed and security, a LAN
relies on wired connections, however,
wireless connections are also used.
LANs using wireless connections are
known as Wireless Local Area Networks.
The protocol used to share data is WiFi
but they can also operate with Bluetooth.
Data can transmit at a fast rate if the
number of linked computers is limited.
They can also connect anything from
two computers to several hundreds.
To connect more than a couple of
machines a hub would be used, this would
link to each machine in the network.
Also, other devices can be linked to a
LAN such as printers for everyone to use.
To connect to the internet or a WAN a
router would be needed rather than a hub.
Abraham: A MAN, or Metropolitan Area
Network covers a larger area than a LAN.
It can connect various
users who are situated in a
specific geographical region.
It can be found within a large
University or Hospital campus, a
telephone company or cable TV network.
It may serve as an ISP
[internet service provider].
The overall goal of a MAN is to
develop the links between LANs.
It is designed for high-speed
connectivity and will use optical
fibres and switches and routers.
Switches perform 2 key functions,
filtering data and managing connections.
Nicole: A WAN or Wide Area Network is
a computer network that extends over
a large specific geographical area.
This may be a large city or a country
or could be the size of the world
if the internet was one entity.
A WAN connects LANs to other
LANs and to MANs using ISPs.
WAN's can be public or private.
An organisation could have a company
WAN which covers small regional offices,
the main head office and cloud services.
Devices used to transmit data
through WAN are optical fibres,
microwaves, and satellites.
WANs by the nature of their size
often have to cross territorial
boundaries and international borders
and as so are subject to different
legal jurisdictions which may in
turn lead to network usage rights.
Often also network cables run under the
sea which can open them up to damage by
weather, marine traffic, or sabotage.
Data sent over networks such as the
internet is divided into packets.
This means large amount of
data is split up so that it
doesn't slow down the system.
It is sent in small packages
through the wires, cables and
radio waves of the internet.
The data is then reconstituted in the
correct order by the recipient’s device.
It is possible theoretically to
send data over the internet without
chopping it into small packets.
It could be sent as a line of bits,
but this approach is impractical when
more than 2 computers are involved.
Abraham: The main two ways in which
packets are sent are TCP and UDP.
TCP ensures that all data packets
arrive where they need to, with
a handshake done to confirm.
An example of this is web traffic – it’s
important you get all the packets so
that the website renders correctly.
UDP does not have a handshake
and sends all packets and
doesn’t care if they all arrive.
An example of UDP traffic is live
video streaming – you wouldn’t want the
whole programme you’re watching to stop
just because one packet representing
a tiny part of the stream didn’t come
through because of a network blip.
The internet is a packet switching
network allowing packets to be
processed independently from each other.
As a result, billions of devices
can exchange data at the same time.
Network traffic is a term that refers
to packets however not all packets are
good and not all network traffic is safe.
Attackers can generate malicious network
traffic designed to compromise or
overwhelm a network in the form of DDoS.